Guide to the Carl Aldo Marzani Papers TAM 154
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Aldo Marzani Papers
1880-1994
1935-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marzani, Tony
Marzani, Charlotte Pomerantz
TAM 154
20.25 Linear Feet in 38 manuscript boxes, one phonograph record box, and one record carton.
Carl Marzani (1912-1994) was an Italian-American immigrant radical and briefly a Communist Party, USA organizer on New York City's Lower East Side. He served in the Office of Strategic Services during World War II and briefly thereafter in the State Department. He was also a political documentary filmmaker, the author of six books and numerous articles, and as an editor and publisher, first translated and published portions of the work of the Italian Marxist, Antonio Gramsci. Marzani served almost three years in prison, from 1947-1950, for concealing his prewar Party membership while he was employed by the government. He lived and worked in New York City most of his life. This collection of papers includes his correspondence, manuscripts, and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Carl Marzani in 1994; additional materials were donated by Tony Marzani in 1995 and Charlotte Pomerantz Marzani in 1998. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1993.004, 1994.010 and NPA.1998.010.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series:
Series I: Biographical: Childhood & Youth
Series II: Trial/Prison Papers
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Writings
Series V: Political Activities
Series VI: Publishing: Cameron Associates, Marzani & Munsell
Series VII: Addendum
Series VIII: Photographs
Historical/Biographical Note
Carl Marzani (1912-1994), Italian-American immigrant radical, was briefly a Communist Party, USA organizer on New York City's Lower East Side, served in the Office of Strategic Services during World War II and briefly thereafter in the State Department, was a political documentary filmmaker, the author of six books and numerous articles, and as an editor and publisher, first translated published portions of the work of the Italian Marxist Antonio Gramsci. Marzani served almost three years in prison, from 1947-1950, for defrauding the United States by concealing his prewar Party membership during the period of his government employment. He lived and worked in New York City most of his life.
Carl Marzani was born in Rome, Italy, on March 4, 1912. Carl's father, Gabriel, was a Socialist, and the family emigrated to the United States in 1924, settling in Scranton, Pennsylvania. In America, Carl entered the first grade at the age of twelve. As his English improved, he became an outstanding student, and in 1931, Carl graduated from Scranton High School and received a scholarship to Williams College.
Once in college, Carl became an avowed Socialist. He joined the League for Industrial Democracy, and wrote stories that reflected his beliefs for the school's literary magazine: Sketch, of which he became editor of in his sophomore year. While still in college, Carl met the woman who would later become his first wife, actress Edith Eisner, whose stage name was Edith Emerson. Marzani graduated summa cum laude from Williams College in 1935, with a BA in English. After graduating, Carl went to New York to look for work, which was scarce due to the depression. In the summer of 1936, he received word from Williams College that he had been awarded a Moody fellowship to Oxford University.
At this point in his life, Carl considered himself a "mild radical". He knew little about Communism and had read nothing on Marxism. However, this changed on the way to England to attend Oxford in late August of 1936, when he read Trotsky's History of the Russian Revolution, which had a profound effect on him. In 1936, the Spanish Civil War broke out, and it became known that Mussolini was backing Franco by sending planes and troops. In late 1936 through early 1937, Carl served as a member of the Durruti Column, the leading anarchist troops in Spain. He then returned to Oxford to complete his studies, and married Edith in Oxford on March 12th 1937. In June 1938, Carl received a BA in Modern Greats; Philosophy, Politics and Economics. While Carl was in Spain, Edith became a Communist. Influenced by Edith, Marzani joined the British Communist Party, and became treasurer of the South Midlands district. In the summer of 1938, Carl and Edith left Oxford with $500 and hitch-hiked around the world, visiting India, Indochina, China, Japan, and Europe, and used their Communist contacts to meet Nehru and other important radicals.
In May of 1939, the Marzanis returned to America, where they moved to New York's Lower East Side. Having difficulties making ends meet, they were on relief, and later got jobs through the Works Progress Administration (WPA). Carl and Edith also both joined the Communist Party, USA, going under the names Tony Whales and Edith Charles. Marzani's WPA job was to work on income studies at New York University. From WPA, Marzani assumed an Assistant Instructor position, and was then promoted to Instructor. During this time, Carl was the district Organizer for the Communist Party on the Lower East Side. After the Soviet Union was invaded, the Communist Party set up a popular front anti-fascist organization, and wanted Marzani to become its director. Marzani agreed, but he resigned from the Communist party in August, 1941, because he felt he could not function in both capacities.
In early 1942 Carl resigned from his job at NYU and went to Washington to help the war effort. From 1942-1945 Marzani worked under Colonel William J. Donovan for the Office of Strategic Services in the Analysis Branch. On August 23, 1943, Marzani was drafted. He served two weeks in the military's basic training program in Virginia, and was then sent back to the OSS. Shortly after, his first child Judith Enrica (Ricky) was born. In 1945, he moved to the Department of State, where he worked as the Deputy Chief of the Presentation Division of the Office of Intelligence. Marzani's most significant work was the preparation of top-secret reports for military leaders, taking complex statistics, and communicating the results in all media including films. He also picked the targets for the Doolittle raid on Tokyo, which took place on April 18, 1942.
In 1946 Marzani decided to leave government service, and founded and directed Union Films, a film documentary company that had contracts with United Electrical and other unions to do documentary films for them. The most important film Deadline for Action, a 40 minute documentary made for the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE-CIO), placed major responsibility for the Cold War on the United States, linking this to the growing attacks on labor unions. The documentary was released in September 1946, five weeks before Marzani resigned from the State Department.
Despite Marzani's honorable service in the OSS, his past membership in the Communist Party and Deadline led to an eleven-count indictment in January, 1947 on charges of fraud -- receiving his government pay while concealing pre-war membership in the Communist Party. At this time, Edith found out that she was pregnant with their second child. On June 22, 1947, Carl Marzani was convicted in a Federal Court in Washington. The Appeals Court threw out nine counts; the Supreme Court (granting a rare rehearing) split 4-4 on the last two. Marzani served thirty-two months of a thirty-six month sentence.
In prison, Marzani studied and made notes for a book, We Can Be Friends: The Origins of the Cold War(1952), showing how Truman started the Cold War. In September of 1947, Edith gave birth to their second child, Anthony (Tony) Hugh. In 1950, Marzani tried to smuggle out a manuscript that he was working on, but was caught, and placed in solitary confinement for seven months. During his stay in prison, Carl and Edith wrote extensively to each other. Edith ran Union Films, raised their two small children, supported Carl's mother, and battled with multiple sclerosis. Union Films folded in 1949, after being harassed by New York City with zoning violations and other restrictions.
After his release from prison in 1951, Marzani worked for the United Electrical Workers, as the Editor for UE Steward, a leadership magazine, until 1954. At this time he joined Cameron Associates, headed by Angus Cameron, a radical editor. Together they ran the Liberty Book Club (established 1948). One of the first books released was Labor's Untold Story, a history of the U.S. labor movement, published for the UE and reflective of its views. After Cameron left, the venture became Marzani & Munsell which operated the Library-Prometheus Book Club. Notable Cameron Associates titles included: False Witness, The Open Marxism of Antonio Gramsci, and Marzani's autobiographical novel, The Survivor.
In 1960 Carl and his first wife, Edith separated in 1961, and divorced in 1966. In 1966, he married Charlotte Pomerantz, a children's book writer. They had two children together. A daughter, Gabrielle Rose was born December 12, 1967, and a son, Daniel Avram, was born February 19, 1969. Also in 1966, Carl's publishing company, Marzani & Munsell, was destroyed in a fire. Carl then went on to purchase, renovate and rent four brownstones in Chelsea, Manhattan( a portion of one of these became his home). Marzani also wrote The Promise of Eurocommunism(1981), and a four volume autobiography, The Education of a Reluctant Radical(1992-1994).
In the late 1980s Carl's health declined. He died on December 11, 1994.
SEE ALSO:
Musser, Charles. "Carl Marzani and Union Films Making Left-Wing Documentaries during the Cold War, 1946-1953." The Moving Image vol. 9, no. 1 (2009): 104-160.
CHRONOLOGY
1912: Born: Rome, Italy March 4th.
1924: Immigrated to the United States on Labor Day.
1935: Graduated from Williams College, BA in English, summa cum laude.
1936: Received Moody Fellowship to Oxford University from Williams College.
1936: Served with Anarchist Durruti Column in Spanish Civil War.
1937: Attended Exeter College, Oxford University 1937, 1938, and enrolled in School of Modern Greats (Philosphy, Politics, Economics) BA in Modern Greats, 1938
1937: Married Edith Eisner, an actress known as Edith Emerson on March 12th.
1937: Marzani joins the Communist Party of Great Britain on August 12th.
1939: Hitch-hiked around the world with Edith Marzani.
1939: Section Organizer, Lower East Side, Communist Party, USA.
1939-1942: Instructor in Economics, New York University.
1942-1945: U.S. Office of Strategic Services. Deputy Division Chief, Presentation Division. Supervision of Intelligence Reports, Studies and Analysis.
1944: First child, Judith Enrica (Ricky) is born on 1/24.
1945-1946: U.S. Department of State: Deputy Division Chief, Office of Intelligence..
1946-1948: Owner of Union Films. Film maker, writer, director, producer of documentaries. Wrote and directed Deadline for Action for the UE-CIO.
1947: Indicted in January on charges of defrauding U.S. Government, by concealing membership in Communist Party.
1947: Anthony (Tony) Hugh Marzani is born in September.
1947-1950: Inmate, various Federal prisons.
1949: Union Films folds.
1950-54: Editor UE Steward for United Electrical Workers, a monthly publication directed to 16,000 shop stewards.
1954-67: Co-Director with Angus Cameron of Liberty Book Club and a publishing firm. Became President of Marzani and Munsell Publishers after Cameron went to Knopf as senior editor.
1966: Edith and Carl divorce.
1966: Carl marries Charlotte Pomerantz, a children's book writer on November 12th.
1966: Fire destroys the firm of Marzani & Munsell.
1967-1983: Carl renovated and operated four brownstones in Chelsea, Manhattan.
1967-1985: Carl and Charlotte have 2 children together: Gabrielle Rose, and Daniel Avram.
Two grandchildren: Jennifer Spector and Max Cutler (both children of Ricki Marzani).
Early 1980s: Lecture tour for The Promise of Eurocommunism.
1994: Publishes Memoirs.
1994: Died on December 12th.
Works by Carl Marzani
BOOKS
1994: The Education of a Reluctant Radical
Book 1 -- Roman Childhood
Book 2 -- Growing Up American
Book 3 -- Spain, Munich, and Dying Empires
Book 4 -- From Pentagon to Penitentiary
1981: The Promise of Eurocommunism
1969: The Wounded Earth: An Environmental Survey
1960: Dollars & Sense of Disarmament, with V. Perlo
1958: The Survivor, a novel:
1952: We Can be Friends--Origins of the Cold War
PAMPHLETS/ESSAYS
1990: On Interring Communism and Exalting Capitalism
1971: The Threat of American Neo-Fascism
1968: The Unspeakable War
1962: The Shelter Hoax & Foreign Policy, editor
1961: Cuba vs. The CIA, with Robert Light
TRANSLATIONS
1959: The Open Marxism of Antonio Gramsci
1959: Inside the Khrushchev Era by Giuseppe Boffa
FILM DOCUMENTARIES
1949: "Our Union" (UE)
1948: "Dollar Patriots"
1947: "The Great Swindle"
1946: "Deadline for Action"
1945: "Air Force Report"
1944: "War Department Report"
Related Materials
Cedric Belfrage Papers (TAM 143)
Carl Marzani Oral Histories (OH 042)
Scope and Content Note
The papers principally contain personal, political, and business correspondence and writings, from the 1930s up until his death in 1994. The bulk of the materials is made up of his work and correspondence as a publisher at Cameron Association and Marzani and Munsell. The collection also contains materials and correspondence related to his trial and imprisonment in 1947 for defrauding the government by receiving government pay while concealing Communist Party membership. The collection also contains some photographs and articles written by Marzani, including his research for his book on George Orwell.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Material
Eighteen audiocassette interviews, conducted in Italy in Italian for Marzani's book The Promise of Eurocommunism, have been been separated to the Library's Oral History collections, as collection# NS42.
Children's book written by Charlotte Pomerantz, Marzani's wife, a run of the Monthly Review, an issue of Marxist Perspectives, and an issue of Etudes D'Economie Politique were separated.
Clippings (information artifacts); Communism -- United States.; Financial records; Printed ephemera.; Correspondence.; Communists -- United States.; Reports.; Manuscripts for publication.; Liberty Book Club; Perlo, Victor; Cameron Associates; Lessing, Doris May, 1919-; Cameron and Kahn; Burgum, Edwin Berry, b. 1894.; Cameron, Angus (Donald Angus) |v Pictorial works; Lowenfels, Walter, 1897-1976.; Orwell, George, 1903-1950.; Lardner, Ring, Jr., 1915-2000; Starobin, Joseph R. (Joseph Robert), 1913-1976.; Snow, Edgar, 1905-1972.; Marzani, Carl -- |v Portraits; Smith, Edwin Burritt, 1854-1906.; Strong, Anna Louise, 1885-1970.; Kahn, Albert Eugene, 1912-1979.; Nelson, Truman John, 1912-; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Dunham, Barrows, 1905-; Baldwin, Calvin Benham, 1902-1975.; Winter, Ella, 1898-1980.; Belfrage, Cedric, 1904-1990.; Heym, Stefan, 1913-2001.; Aptheker, Herbert, 1915-2003.; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003.; France, Royal W.; Ward, Henry Frederick, 1873-1966.; Prometheus Book Club; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; McWilliams, Carey, 1905-1980.; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Maltz, Albert, 1908-1985.; Biberman, H. J. (Herbert); Marzani & Munsell, Publishers (New York, N.Y.); Marzani, Tony; Marzani, Charlotte Pomerantz
- Series I: Biographical: Childhood and Youth, 1890-1941
  Scope and Content Note
  Contains personal papers of the Marzani family, beginning with Carl's parent's legal documents from Rome, dated 1890s, (such as Italian passports). Also included are Carl Marzani's report cards from elementary schools in Rome, and his high school and college literary periodicals, of which he acted as editor. Of particular note are the journals that Carl and Edith Marzani kept while they hitch-hiked around the world, which reveal their growing interest in politics (Box 2, folders 6 & 7).
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Gabriel, Nona, Carl and Marcella Marzani, [1890-1929] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Childhood, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scranton, [1920]-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Impressions: Scranton Central High School, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Williams College, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Williams College: 40th and 50th Reunion Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sketch: The Literary Monthly of Williams College., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Gulielmensian 1936/Williams College. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sketch: The Literary Monthly of Williams College, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - History of Gargoyle 1895-1985 (Williams College Publication), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oxford, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Copy of Edith and Carl's marriage certificate, Mar 12, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings/Photographs, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Journal Kept by Carl Marzani, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Journal Kept by Edith Marzani, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - NYU, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Trial/Prison Papers, 1947-1966
  The largest portion of this series consists of Marzani's FBI file (mostly photocopies of clippings) on his case, obtained under the Freedom of Information Act. There are also the letters of petition from a variety of activists, and other important figures, who banded together in defense of Carl Marzani. Of particular note is a copy of a handwritten letter in German, and a typed, translated copy of a letter from Albert Einstein dated June 24, 1949 to the President of the United State asking for clemency on Marzani's behalf, (Box 3, folder 5). There is a published article written by Eleanor Roosevelt in Marzani's behalf, and law briefs, and a summary of the indictment.
  - USA vs. CAM: Clippings, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - USA vs. CAM: Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - USA vs. CAM: Clippings, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - USA vs. CAM: Clippings, 1953-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - USA vs. CAM: Official Correspondence Prison, Parole, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - USA vs. CAM: Committee in Defense of CAM, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - USA vs CAM: District Court, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - USA vs CAM: Search for Press Support, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - USA vs CAM: Printed Briefs, legal papers, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1935-1995
  This series reflects the range of Marzani's personal correspondence, from love letters to political activity. Early letters from Carl to Edith, written from Oxford, reveal Carl's desire to become a playwright. The letters also reflect Carl's growing interest in politics. The prison correspondence between Carl and Edith Marzani is comprehensive, and also reveal Edith Marzani's strength of character. Stricken with multiple sclerosis, and in care of two young children, Edith carried on the business of Union Films while Carl served his prison sentence. Of particular note is a letter to Marzani from the FBI containing a copy of a statement concerning present and prior political activities that he made under oath on 7/29/42. There is also a transcript of the testimony before Investigative Agents on the Civil Service Commission taken on Nov. 23, 1942, which reveals the government's prior knowledge of Marzani's political activities. Proof of Carl's dedication while working for the OSS is reflected in a letter written to General Donovan from Robert Patterson (Under Secretary of War) congratulating him on the fine work achieved by his team (including Marzani). There is correspondence between Marzani and his attorney Alan Rosenberg which illustrates Alan Rosenberg's loyalty and their growing friendship. After Carl died, his son Tony maintained correspondence with family, friends, and business relations until 1995.
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Alan Rosenberg, Lawyer, 1947-1951 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Jun 1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jul-Dec 1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Swindle, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Swindle - Inczedy, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Jun 1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jun-Dec 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Jun 1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jul-Dec 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence "Tow-Away Mess", 1983-1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Thank you letters for Political Contributions, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Jun 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jul-Dec 1993 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Undated & Misc. (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Writings, undated, 1957-1987
  This series contains drafts of, and notes for, various manuscripts written by Marzani. The bulk of the material pertains to the major project of his later years, the unpublished work titled, George Orwell. This work principally dealt with the origins and history of the Cold War, and also critiqued Orwell's reportage of the Spanish Civil War. There are also materials pertaining to The Promise of Eurocommunism, The Survivor, and other works.
  - Orwell I to IV Early footnotes, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Orwell notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Orwell. Version of essay, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Orwell: Possible footnotes, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Orwell: footnotes, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Orwell: Footnotes I, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Part II: Orwell and Spain, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)